<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-08T10:52:32+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Emiel Lemahieu</title><subtitle>Quantitative Researcher</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Generating drawdown-realistic markets using path signatures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/generating-drawdown-realistic-markets-using-path-signatures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generating drawdown-realistic markets using path signatures" /><published>2023-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/generating-drawdown-realistic-markets-using-path-signatures</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/generating-drawdown-realistic-markets-using-path-signatures"><![CDATA[<hr />

<p>The simulation of markets with drawdowns that are faithful to empirical market data is a challenging task as drawdown is a path dependent property depending on both the moments of the underlying price process as well as its dynamics such as the occurrence of consecutive losses. In applications, such as pricing drawdown insurance options or developing portfolio drawdown control or optimization strategies, it is paramount that one reproduces this measure correctly in synthetic scenarios. We advocate an essentially non-parametric Monte Carlo approach from machine learning, combining a variational autoencoder generative model with a path signature-based drawdown reconstruction loss function. Machine learning requires a system of differentiable equations that provides numerical simulations by iteration or learning. To overcome issues of numerical complexity and non-differentiability, we approximate drawdown as a linear function of its dynamic or path moments, known in the literature as path signatures. For (fractional) Brownian and empirical data, we obtain excellent approximations using simple linear regression. We then appreciate that drawdown as a linear combination of path moments gives a mathematically non-trivial smoothing (a non-commutative exponential alternative for Taylor series) which gives one leeway to simulate drawdown-realistic markets by including a drawdown evaluation metric in the learning objective. We conclude with a number of numerical experiments on mixed equity, bond, real-estate and commodity portfolios and obtain a host of realistic drawdown scenarios.</p>

<h6 id="preview">Preview</h6>
<iframe src="../assets/Generating_drawdown_realistic_markets_with_path_signatures___PROPOSITIONS (2).pdf#view=FitV" style="width: 70%; height: 50vh"></iframe>

<h6 id="download">Download</h6>
<p>Download the pdf below :</p>

<p><a href="../assets/Generating_drawdown_realistic_markets_with_path_signatures___PROPOSITIONS (2).pdf">Generating drawdown-realistic markets using path signatures</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Market Generators" /><category term="Drawdowns" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Working paper - Generating drawdown-realistic markets with generative AI and path signatures]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Explainable data-driven portfolio construction with conditional bootstrapped Shapley values</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/explainable-data-driven-portfolio-construction-with-conditional-bootstrapped-shapley-values" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explainable data-driven portfolio construction with conditional bootstrapped Shapley values" /><published>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/explainable-data-driven-portfolio-construction-with-conditional-bootstrapped-shapley-values</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/explainable-data-driven-portfolio-construction-with-conditional-bootstrapped-shapley-values"><![CDATA[<hr />

<p>Data-driven portfolio construction is non-parametric in the sense that it does not impose its objective on a parametric representation of input paths, such as a variance-covariance matrix, but rather imposes its objective directly on these paths without having to make assumptions on their underlying data generating process (DGP). The advantage is thus that one can optimize on much richer dynamics than typical DGP assumptions, e.g. Gaussian assumptions behind mean-variance optimization. The main disadvantage is that one can seemingly interpret the parameters that gave rise to the optimal portfolios not that easily anymore, and for instance do sensitivity analysis, i.e. how will the portfolio change when parameter x or y in- or decreases? This is conducive to the black box perception of increasingly more data-driven portfolio construction tools. However, tools from explainable AI such as Shapley values, which are mathematically principled contribution estimators of features to their output, can be used to overcome this issue. We advocate a novel approach that combines the powerful statistical approach of conditional bootstrapping with Shapley values that attribute changing optimal portfolio weights to changing market conditions. The empirical usefulness is shown on a US equity portfolio backtest, where the portfolio manager gets a better insight in his or her portfolio composition and its sensitivity to changing market conditions.</p>

<h6 id="preview">Preview</h6>
<iframe src="../assets/Explainable_non_parametric_portfolio_construction_with_conditional_bootstrapped_Shapley_values (9).pdf#view=FitV" style="width: 70%; height: 50vh"></iframe>

<h6 id="download">Download</h6>
<p>Download the pdf below:</p>

<p><a href="../assets/Explainable_non_parametric_portfolio_construction_with_conditional_bootstrapped_Shapley_values (9).pdf">Explainable data-driven portfolio construction with conditional bootstrapped Shapley values</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Market Generators" /><category term="Drawdowns" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Working paper - Explaining DGP-free portfolio construction with SHAP values]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">R/Finance 2022 - Portfolio drawdown optimization with generative machine learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/rfinance-portfolio-drawdown-optimization-with-generative-machine-learning" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="R/Finance 2022 - Portfolio drawdown optimization with generative machine learning" /><published>2022-06-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/rfinance-portfolio-drawdown-optimization-with-generative-machine-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/rfinance-portfolio-drawdown-optimization-with-generative-machine-learning"><![CDATA[<p>This short paper was presented at the 2022 R/Finance conference in Chicago, IL. It picks one of the above-mentioned architectures - a CVAE - and introduces a signature-based drawdown reconstruction cost loss term. The result is a host of realistic drawdown scenarios, where the optimal portfolio is defined as the ensemble expectation of min drawdown optimizers.</p>

<h6 id="preview">Preview</h6>
<iframe src="../assets/Portfolio_drawdown_optimization_with_generative_machine_learning___opportunities_and_pitfalls__RFinance.pdf#view=FitV" style="width: 70%; height: 50vh"></iframe>

<h6 id="download">Download</h6>
<p>Download the pdf below:</p>

<p><a href="../assets/Portfolio_drawdown_optimization_with_generative_machine_learning___opportunities_and_pitfalls__RFinance.pdf">Portfolio drawdown optimization with generative machine learning</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Market Generators" /><category term="Drawdowns" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[R/Finance conference paper - Generating drawdown-optimal portfolios with generative AI]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Market Generator models - A literature review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/market-generators-literature-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Market Generator models - A literature review" /><published>2022-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/market-generators-literature-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/market-generators-literature-review"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Market generators</strong> are generative machine learning (ML) models with the specificity of modeling financial markets - such as stocks’ spot markets, options’ vol surfaces and limit order books (market microstructure).</p>

<p>The topic has seen a recent surge in interest, and this literature review provides a (non-exhaustive) list of the most important contributions in the field. Moreover, it discusses the following generative ML architectures in detail:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Generative Adversarial Networks (GAN)</li>
  <li>Variational Autoencoders (VAE)</li>
  <li>Restricted Boltzmann Machines (RBM)</li>
  <li>Generative Moment Matching Networks (GMMN)</li>
  <li>Normalizing flow-based autoencoders (NF)</li>
</ul>

<p>Additionally, the literature review describes how each model can be conditioned on some exogenous state variables X to compose a conditional VAE (CVAE), conditional GAN (CGAN), etc. architecture. A good example would be to condition the simulation on the state-of-the-economy by including leading macro-economic indicators. In a portfolio construction context, the differences in optimal portfolios resulting from the conditional simulation can then be attributed to the conditions and sensitivities analyzed. A very simple example is included in the literature review.</p>

<h6 id="preview-summary">Preview summary</h6>
<iframe src="../assets/Literature_review_slides.pdf#view=FitV" style="width: 70%; height: 50vh"></iframe>

<h6 id="download-summary">Download summary</h6>
<p>Download a slide summary below:</p>

<p><a href="../assets/Literature_review_slides.pdf">Slide summary - Market Generator models: A literature review</a>.</p>

<h6 id="preview-main-text">Preview main text</h6>
<iframe src="../assets/Literature_review.pdf#view=FitV" style="width: 70%; height: 50vh"></iframe>

<h6 id="download-main-text">Download main text</h6>
<p>Download the full pdf below:</p>

<p><a href="../assets/Literature_review.pdf">Market Generator models: A literature review</a>.</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Market Generators" /><category term="Drawdowns" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A literature review of the market generator literature]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Signatures for drawdown paths - A primer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/signatures-for-drawdown-paths-a-primer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Signatures for drawdown paths - A primer" /><published>2021-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/signatures-for-drawdown-paths-a-primer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/signatures-for-drawdown-paths-a-primer"><![CDATA[<p>My other projects hinge on the concepts of <strong>paths</strong> and <strong>path signatures</strong> as prerequisites. In the words of Terry Lyons<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The key idea behind signatures is to stop thinking about a path as a quantity evolving over time, but rather as an object that you can query over intervals. As one queries these intervals, one gets a natural description about what happens with the system at different time scales.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The primer (based on <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1603.03788">Chevyrev et al. 2016</a>) compiles my notes from a literature review on the signature transform, and includes two examples related to portfolio drawdown:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Classifying high- and low-drawdown stocks in terms of next period expectation using signature transformed previous period paths as features.</li>
  <li>Distinguishing between high- and low-codrawdown regimes using signature embedded paths.</li>
</ul>

<h6 id="preview">Preview</h6>
<iframe src="../assets/Signatures_drawdowns_primer.pdf#view=FitV" style="width: 70%; height: 50vh"></iframe>

<h6 id="download">Download</h6>
<p>Download the pdf below:</p>

<p><a href="../assets/Signatures_drawdowns_primer.pdf">Signatures for drawdown paths: A primer</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="references">References</h3>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RnpHG5pRwZ8?start=117" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Reference to this quote and highly recommended is this introduction to signatures and rough path theory given by Terry Lyons at the Royal Statistical Society in 2022 included above. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Signature transform" /><category term="Drawdowns" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A primer into using signature transform for modeling drawdowns]]></summary></entry></feed>